Today's דף daf is the last דף daf of כ"ח Chof-Ches and
we will do the few lines of כ"ט Chof-Tes and we will
finish the מסכת. masechet. So no questions today, here we go. Last
line of כ"ז עמוד ב'. Chof-Zayin Amud Bais. שלשה נשים לעולם מן
הקבור, Shlosha nashim l'olam min hakavor, we do not let the women's
coffin lay in the street even on חול המועד Chol HaMoed due
to respect. אמרי נהרדעי, Amre Nehardae, the Nehardaeans said, לא שנו, lo
shanu, כ"ח עמוד א', Chof-Ches Amud Aleph, אלא חיה, ela chaya, that's
not all women, that's only a woman who has just given birth,
who has died in the process of childbirth and therefore the body
is in a state
of fluids coming out and so on, it's the concern of disfigurement,
אבל שאר נשים מניחין, aval sh'ar nashim m'nichim, other women you would,
in order to wait to get people to gather and to be
מספיד, maspid, eulogize and do the wailing and so on. רבי אליעזר
אומר אפילו שאר נשים, Rabbi Eliezer omer afilu sh'ar nashim, no, take
the משנה Mishnah literally, even other women, דכתיב ותמת שם מרים ותקבר
שם, d'ksiv vatamas sham Miriam vatikaver sham,
Miriam died there and she was buried there, so immediately after she
died, she was buried, סמוך
למיתה קבורה. somuch l'misa kevura. So this suggests immediately after she died
she was buried, so we do not prolong the process of getting
the body buried in the case of women. Again, I don't exactly
fully understand what the aspects of כבוד kavod were, which are very
societally contextual, but that clearly was understood to be an issue based
on this verse. ואמר רבי אלעזר אף מרים בנשיקה מתה, v'omar Rabbi
Elazar af Miriam b'nishika mesa, now that we're talking about Miriam's death,
we say Miriam died with the divine kiss, which we'll see is
based on a verse by Moshe where it says על פי ה',
al pi Hashem, by the mouth of God as if they were
kissed, meaning that the death was very pleasant, was very smooth,
and that sense also about the soul presumably, the intimacy with God
that the soul goes to after death. אתיא שם שם ממשה, asha
sham sham miMoshe, we make a גזירה שוה gzera shava from Moshe,
because it says ותמת שם vatamas sham and by Moshe it says
וימת שם. vayamas sham. מפני מה לא נאמר בה על פי ה',
mipnei ma lo ne'emar ba al pi Hashem, so if it's true,
why was it not said explicitly by her that she died by
the mouth of God? מפני שגנאי הדבר לאומרו, mipnei shegnai hadavar l'omro,
because it sounds presumably too sexual to speak that the
kiss between God and Miriam, which would be less of a concern
in the case of Moshe. אמר רבי אמי למה נסמכה מיתת מרים
לפרשת פרה אדומה, Amar Rabbi Ami lama nism'cha misas Miriam l'parshas para
aduma, why is the death of Miriam linked to פרה אדומה para
aduma meaning or juxtaposed in the תורה? Torah? לומר לך מה פרה
אדומה מכפרת אף מיתתן של צדיקים מכפרת, lomar lach mah para aduma
m'chaperes af misas tzadikkim m'chaperes,
the same way פרה אדומה para aduma atones, the death of the
righteous atones. Now that's a little bit of a strange idea because
if you would ask me which are the sacrifices that atone, I
probably would have put פרה אדומה para aduma somewhere on the bottom
of the list. I mean, I don't know if I would have
even put it on the list, you don't normally think about something
that's atoning, it is called a חטאת, chatas,
but both of these do have an interesting idea that it is
פרה אדומה para aduma is something, we're learning about this also in
the ישיבה yeshiva in the morning about the שעיר המשתלח Seir Hamishtaleach
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, about certain types of pseudo-קרבנות korbonos that
were brought outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and they create a
fascinating little set like the פרה אדומה, para aduma, עגלה ערופה, egla
arufa, שעיר המשתלח. Seir Hamishtaleach.
And understood that
way, with the death of righteous, again, this is an idea that
we tend to say oh that's a Christian idea, but they got
it from somewhere,
this is actually very in the גמרא Gemara and possibly even earlier,
whether or not we're comfortable with it or not, that the מיתת
צדיקים misas tzadikkim brings about atonement and it is, there is similarity
here, like it's outside of the מקדש, Mikdash, it's a life that
is being given
over and somehow that is seen as effecting atonement. So the comparison
to פרה אדומה para aduma here makes a certain amount of sense
in that it is a giving of a life outside of the
מקדש. Mikdash.
Okay, so אמר רבי אלעזר למה נסמכה מיתת אהרן לבגדי כהונה, Amar
Rabbi Elazar lama nism'cha misas Aharon l'bigdei kehuna, now why is the
death of אהרן Aharon compared to בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna meaning not
compared or juxtaposed, the whole thing is preceded by him being removed
the vestments and being dressed and אלעזר Elazar being dressed by them,
but it's
used for this דרשה drasha to tell you מה בגדי כהונה מכפרין
אף מיתתן של צדיקים מכפרת, mah bigdei kehuna m'chaprin af misas tzadikkim
m'chaperes,
the same way the garments of the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna are
מכפר m'chaper which the גמרא Gemara learned out elsewhere, certainly you have
פסוקים psukim about אהרן Aharon carrying עון הקדשים avon hakodashim when he
wears certain בגדים. bigadim. So similarly also the מיתת צדיקים misas tzadikkim
is מכפר, m'chaper, so here it's not as גנאי gnai of an
analogy as I was suggesting before by the פרה אדומה. para aduma.
It's harder to understand exactly what the comparison here is other than
to make that statement that the מיתת צדיקים misas tzadikkim is מכפר.
m'chaper. It is interesting you know here again at the end of
the מסכת. masechet. and we're going to see very soon as well
about trying to grapple with what we saw yesterday was dealing with
the issue of like excessive grief and trying to grapple with the
question about, you know, do it like what's a healthy grieving process
as opposed to a non-healthy grieving process. It is true that the
response in the גמרא Gemara seems very harsh, you know, that one
story, but nevertheless, you know, until now it's an interesting to see
the shift at the end that we've been dealing with הלכות halachot
of אבילות avelut and now we sort of turn to what you
know sort of pastoral, theological, other issues around אבילות. avelut. So yesterday
there was a discussion about like healthy grieving as opposed to unhealthy
grieving, and here it seems to be pointing about thinking a little
bit about the theological implications. What does the death mean? So at
least by the צדיקים, tzaddikim, a framework of understanding that it's the
you know how is it that this righteous person who's so righteous
why did they die how did the you know what what is
this about seeing it in a sort of positive way religious theological
way that it's to bring atonement for the generation, you know, for
the people and so on. Again acknowledging that that might be challenging
for our for our theology maybe it is maybe it isn't also
has echoes you know in Christianity or more than echoes but anyway
at least that's where we're moving now as the מסכת masechet is
drawing to a close. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan and with that in
mind now we look at the issues of death and how to
understand the significance of of how people are dying what is it
telling us about the person or about their life and so on.
תנו רבנן tanu rabanan מת פתאום met pitom if someone dies suddenly
without there at least a chance of getting sick and everybody him
having a chance or her having a chance to prepare him or
herself for the death the family having a chance it's just a
sudden death heart attack sudden death car accident something like that זו
היא מיתה חטופה zu hi mita chatufa it's a death that was
grabbed like you know it's it's rushed which is not necessarily healthy
or whatever or it's not necessarily the best. חלה יום אחד chala
yom echad if it was a one day illness ומת umet זו
היא מיתה דחופה zu hi mita dchufa it's rushed it's which is
less than grabbed you know snatched actually would be the better word
but it's rushed. ורבי חנינא בן גמליאל אומר veRabbi Chanina ben Gamliel
omer זו היא מיתה מגפה zu hi mita mageifa actually that's the
death of a plague שנאמר shene'emar בן אדם הנני לוקח ממך את
מחמד עיניך במגפה ben adam hinni loke'ach mimcha et machmad einecha bemageifa
I will take the desired thing of your eyes your wife from
you in a plague וכתיב uchtiv ואדבר אל העם בבוקר ותמת אשתי
בערב va'adaber el ha'am baboker vatamas ishti ba'arev I spoke to the
people in the morning and she died at night so one day
after he was informed she died. שני ימים shenei yamim two days
ומת umet זו היא מיתה דחויה zu hi mita dchuya it is
pressured I guess we'll we'll translate it that way which is a
little bit less than than rushed. ג' גערה gimmel ge'ara three days
is like a yelling ד' נזיפה arba nezifa four is a I
have no idea four is some type of you know also insult
וחמישה vachamisha זו היא מיתת כל אדם. zu hi mitat kol adam.
Now take a look at תוספות tosafot תוספות tosafot asks Michael's question
חטופה chatufa דחופה dchufa לא ידענא מאי שנא הוא ומנא ליה lo
yadana mai shna hu u'minalei I don't know what the difference is
between snatched and rushed and pushed and pressured and I don't even
know where they're getting this from. Okay but what they're certainly laying
out is an idea you know again how is this supposed to
make people feel when relatives die in one two or three days
but they're trying to make people feel like you know having a
short period of illness to sort of prepare everyone you know and
sort of and is is a healthy experience not that people can
do anything about it one way or the other.
Okay now to continues.
Okay אמר רבי חנינא מאי קרא amar Rabbi Chanina mai kra what's
the verse that like הן קרבו ימיך למות hen karevu yamecha lamut
behold your days have drawn clear to die. הן hen חד chad
hen means one as we'll see in Greek it means one קרבו
karevu תרי trei karevu is in plural it's two ימיך yamecha תרי
trei הא חמישה ha chamisha it's five. Of course as תוספות tosafot
points out Moshe was supposedly healthy and you know until the very
last day that he died but okay. הן hen חד chad שכן
קורין בלשון יווני קורין לאחד הן. sheken korin bilshon yavani korin leachad
hen. Okay and somehow in Greek I don't know what how do
you say one in Greek anybody hen maybe what uni
I'm sorry uni uni uni
uni aha so that could be. And actually the heh you know
is there's a question about if you if you know about it
might have been pronounced more like an alef because there's some evidence
of that that about like or at least the the Greeks could've
I don't know there's something about about hen being pronounced as en
I know there's like some discussion on that. Anyway okay fine so
that's interesting okay so anyway so therefore you have this idea.
מת בחמישים שנה met bachamishim shana now we're moving from how quickly
the death occurred to how old the person was. If somebody dies
in fifty years question does this mean as we'll see between fifty
and sixty does it mean less than fifty anyway let's but let's
keep on reading. זו היא מיתת כרת zu hi mitat kares that's
a mita of kares like when the Torah speaks about a person
being ונכרת venichrat cut off here it's understood to mean a short
life which is dying by fifty. חמישים ושתים שנה chamishim ushtayim shana
if somebody dies at fifty-two זו היא מיתתו של שמואל הרמתי zu
hi mitato shel Shmuel HaRamati that's when Shmuel died okay so what
does I don't know right. שישים זו היא מיתה בידי shishim zu
hi mita bidei שישים shishim זו היא מיתה בידי שמיים. zu hi
misa bidei shamayim. Sixty is a death through the hands of heaven.
Is that a good thing or a bad thing? Right? Because sometimes
we talk about a certain עבירה aveirah being punished by מיתה בידי
שמיים. misa bidei shamayim. So that's supposed to be saying that that's
a natural death or is that supposed to be saying that's a
bad thing? אמר מר זוטרא amar Mar Zutra מאי קרא mai kra
דכתיב, dichtiv, so here it is going to be understood as a
good thing because the verse says תבא בכלח אלי קבר, tavo be'chelach
alei kever, come into normally translated as an old age into the
ground. בכלח bakelach בגימטריא שיתין הוו, begematria shishin havu,
and בכלח bakelach is you do the gematria sixty so presumably sixty
is a good death, is a ripe age. שבעים, shivim,
now obviously this was a time when people died at a younger
age even if they lived through childhood because whatever the medicine was
not as advanced. שבעים, shivim, so sixty is a nice, is a
natural death, an average age to die. שבעים שיבה, shivim seiva, seventy
is old age. שמונים
גבורות, shmonim gevuros, שמונים shmonim is eighty is a real hoary age,
שכתוב she'chtiv ימי שנותינו בהם שבעים שנה, yemei shnosenu bahem shivim shana,
our years are seventy, ואם בגבורות v'im bigvuros and if we're really
strong, שמונים שנה shmonim shana then live to eighty years. אמר רבא,
amar Rava, so again not exactly clear some of this other stuff,
what the story is when it says fifty. Does it mean up
to fifty is כרת? kares? To fifty to sixty is כרת? kares?
So רבא Rava explains, אמר רבא amar Rava מחמישים עד שישים שנה
זו היא מיתת כרת, mechamishim ad shishim shana zu hi misas kares,
from fifty to sixty is כרת. kares. So that would make that
שמואל הרמתי Shmuel HaRamasi died during the age of כרת. kares. והאידנא
לא חשיב להו? veha'idna lo chashiv lehu? So why didn't they spell
it out? Why did it just say fifty? Why didn't they say
fifty to sixty? משום כבודו של שמואל הרמתי mishum kvodo shel Shmuel
HaRamasi
because it didn't want to point out that שמואל Shmuel died during
that period. What are we supposed to do with that information? What
does that mean? I don't know. Okay. רב יוסף כי הוה בר
שיתין, Rav Yosef ki hava bar shishin, when רב יוסף Rav Yosef
turned sixty עבד להו יומא טבא לרבנן, avid lehu yoma tava lerabanan,
he made a party for the rabbis, אמר amar נפקי לי מכרת
nafki li mikares ברוך השם, baruch Hashem,
I've lived outside of the age of כרת. kares. So whenever I
die now won't be such a bad סימן. siman. אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye who was one of his students
said to him, מהא דנפק ליה מר מכרת דשני, m'hi de'nafik lei
mar mikares de'shanei,
it's true you got out of the כרת kares of years which
is dying under sixty, אבל מכרת דיומי מי נפק מר? aval mikares
deyomi mi nafik mar? But how do you know you got out
of the כרת kares of days? Meaning that we spoke before that,
that if someone dies in one day, two days, three days, four
days. Maybe there'll be a bad סימן siman based on how many
days it takes you to die which is, okay, with a student
like this אמר ליה amar lei נקוט לך מיהא פלגא בידך. nekot
lach mi'palga beyadach. Okay
but at least half I figured, half I got out of. So
we'll worry about the other half later. All right. Anyway, obviously one
wonders how healthy this type of thinking about things are, thinking, wondering
the anxiety around yourself when you're dying, about the family if you
don't fit into these
categories, but clearly they gave this if you see a very much
sort of much more sort of השגחה פרטית hashgacha pratis involved and
then so you look for signs when somebody is dying about what
that signifies about the person and their life. רב הונא נח נפשיה
פתאום, Rav Huna nach nafshia pito'm, so רב הונא Rav Huna died
suddenly and we've seen before that that's not a good thing, הוו
קא דייגי רבנן, hava kadeigi rabanan,
so the rabbis were very were very worried, what does this signify
about רב הונא? Rav Huna? So here's a response to this. Here
a great rabbi died in this way that signifies something bad. תנו
להו זוגא דמהדיב, tanu lehu zugga de'mihadaiv,
a pair of students from this place Hadai'v taught to them, לא
שנו אלא שלא הגיע לגבורות, lo shanu ela shelo higia ligvuros, אבל
הגיע לגבורות aval higia ligvuros זו היא מיתת נשיקה. zu hi misas
neshika.
So we can as we can outweigh the question about the suddenness
of the death, the כרת דיומי kares deyomi based on the age.
So since he was eighty years old, eighty years old and to
die suddenly, that's a death of a divine kiss. That's a
very he went off in his sleep. So if it's when somebody
is younger and more in their vigor that they die suddenly, that's
a bad sign. But when somebody is very old and they die
like they die at night in their sleep, that's a very positive
sign. אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, חיי בני ומזוני לא
בזכותא תליא מילתא אלא במזלא תליא מילתא. chayei benei u'zonei lo bizchusa
talia milsa ela b'mazla talia milsa. So now here you get a
very counter-voice because we're already seeing again it's very troubling to have
these categories and when they and based on what happens to certain
people what it implies about them. So רבא Rava now says don't
start looking for significance here about what a person's merit or deeds
and how it's signified by how a person dies. The life of
a person's life, children, and their מזונות, mezonos, the length, what was
it, the life of length of person's life, children, and מזונות, mezonos,
which means like financial success, is not based on a person's righteousness
and merit, just based on chance and luck and fortune. People, different
people have similar types of merit and one person winds up being
very successful in these areas and another not, and we should not
go ahead and look for this as סימנים, simanim, indicators of the
person's righteousness. And now we're going to give empirical evidence. You've got
to love this, the גמרא Gemara is actually saying it's all nice
to have these categories let's look at some empirical evidence. How do
I know this? דהא
רבה ורב חסדא תרוייהו רבנן צדיקי הוו. Deha Rava ve'Rav Chisda tarvaihu
rabanan tzadiki havu. Rava and Rav Chisda were both very righteous rabbis.
מר—and Mar here's my evidence to it, like I said, how do
you know they were righteous, maybe you don't know, maybe one is
much more righteous than the other—well look, here's my evidence. מר מצלי
ואתי מיטרא, Mar matzli va'asi mitra, when one person would pray rain
would come when there was a drought and this is what we
learned in תענית Taanit about how that's so much signifying access to
God and merit and God's connectedness, ומר מצלי ואתי מיטרא U'mar matzli
va'asi mitra and the other one when he would pray when rain
was needed and rain would come. So first I've got evidence that
they're both at a very high level of צדקות. Tzidkus. Now, רב
חסדא חיה תשעין ותרתי שנין. Rav Chisda chaya tishin ve'tarti shanim. Now
Rav Chisda lived 92 years. רבה חיה ארבעין Rava chaya arbaim and
Rava only lived 40. בי רב חסדא שיתין הלולי Be Rav Chisda
shishin hilulei and in the house of Rav Chisda there were 60
wedding parties, which is probably an exaggeration, whatever, תוספות Tosafot says, you
know, it's לאו דווקא, lav davka, but whatever, you know, they were
always rejoicing. בי רבה שיתין תכלי Be Rava shishin tichlei and in
Rava's house there were 60 anguishes, some even interpret this as being
like
mournings, you know, deaths, funerals, right, or at least tragedy. Okay, so
in Rav Chisda's house there was always a party, always a שמחה,
simcha, in Rava's house it was always a tragedy, there was always
צרות. tzaros. בי רב חסדא סמידא לכלבי ולא מתבעי Be Rav Chisda
samida le'kalbi velo mitba'ei in Rav Chisda's house you could feed like
fine flour to the dogs and you know that wouldn't be a
problem, like you know they would have, you know, even the best
of food for their dogs. בי רבה נהמא דשערי לאינשי ולא משתכחא,
Be Rava nama de'se'ari le'inshi velo mishtakcha, in Rava's house even you
want just barley bread for people, and nobody could afford it. So
you see, very righteous and nevertheless, you know, look, you know, the
years of life were different, what happened with their children, did they
have a lot of kids, did they marry off their children or
did their children die, you know, that's the בני benin and the
מזוני, mezonas, all these things had nothing to do with righteousness. So
let's not go looking for סימנים simanim about these, you know, in
terms of what this indicates about a person's righteousness. So that I
think is a type of an approach that much more resonates for
us in general should be much more healthy. You don't live to
the right—what happened like here, what went—who was it that died? When
רב הונא, Rav Huna, you know, you have all this anxiety, what
does it mean about our רבי, Rebbe, what does it mean about
our father, our mother, whatever, we thought she was so righteous, look
what she died, you know, so this is a, don't worry about
any of that.
Don't even think like for about that.
Well, that's true. Okay. ואמר רבה הני תלת מילי בעי קמי שמיא.
Ve'amar Rava hani talas mili ba'i kamei shamaya. Now Rava said these
three things, הני תלת מילי בעי קמי שמיא, hani talas mili ba'i
kamei shamaya, I asked from God, I asked from heaven. תרתי יהבו
לי וחדא לא יהבו לי, Tarti yehavu li vachada lo yehavu li,
two were given to me and one was not given to me.
חכמתיה דרב הונא, Chochmasei de'Rav Huna, I wanted have the wisdom of
Rav Huna, ועותרא דרב חסדא ve'osrei de'Rav Chisda
and the wealth of Rav Chisda, ויהבו לי. vi'yehavu li. That I
got, wisdom and wealth, so he's already doing like better than שלמה
Shlomo or something. Anyway, וענוותנותיה דרבה בר רב הונא ve'anvesanusei de'Rabba bar
Rav Huna but the humility of Rabba bar Rav Huna, ולא יהבו
לי. velo yehavu li. That they didn't give me. There's gotta be
some joke there. Okay. רב סאורין אחוה דרבה. Rav Se'orin achua de'Rava.
Now רב סאורין, Rav Se'orin, I'm not exactly clear by the way
about how that, I mean whatever, that fits in because it's about
what you get from God doesn't can't always explain the success or
whatever about what someone gets from God, but it is a little
bit of a counter-voice and it's the same רבה Rava that's saying
it. One is attributing it to מזל, mazal, which sees God as
not involved at all, and the other says that actually these types
of things of success, wisdom, wealth,
etc., although two out of these three were more personal characteristics than
they were about chance, right, wisdom and humility, but anyway, but here
it sees God as much more directly involved in those things. So
it is an interesting counter-voice. Now, רב סאורין אחוה דרבה הוה. Rav
Se'orin achua de'Rava hava. Rav Se'orin was the brother of Rava. יתיב
קמיה דרבה, Yasiv kamei de'Rava, he was sitting in front of Rava.
חזיה דהוה קמנמנם. Chazyei de'hava kameinamnem. Rava, נמנם namnam often means dozing
off, but in this context it also means that he was like
sliding away and dying. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
Rava—I'm sorry, Rava said to him, to Rav Se'orin his brother—לימא ליה
מר דלא ליצערן. Lemei lei Mar d'lo litzaran. Tell, you know, you
should tell him, him meaning the מלאך המות, Malach Hamaves, not to
cause me anguish as I die. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
said back to him, מר לאו שושביניה הוא? Mar lav shushpinei hu?
Wait a minute, aren't you his pal? Meaning like, you know, you're
like so righteous, you're more of a colleague of these divine angels,
so you tell him not to cause you צער. tza'ar. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so then Rava said to him, No, כיון דאימסר מזלא
לא אשגח בי. Keivan de'imsar mazla lo ashgach bi.
Once my מזל mazal is given over, once I'm in the process
of dying, he's not going to pay attention to me. Like he'll
pay more attention to the living than the people that are being
taken away and in the process of dying. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
okay, so whatever happened with that we don't know, but anyway, then
Rav Se'orin said to him, ליחזי לי מר, Leitchezi lei Mar, appear
to me after you die. איתחזי ליה, Itchezi lei, so Rava appeared
to him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so Rav Se'orin said to Rava
now to his, Rava's disembodied spirit, הוה ליה מר צערא, Hava lei
Mar tza'ara, did you have pain when you were dying? אמר ליה
כביזתא דכוסילתא, Amar lei kividit de'chusilta,
like the sort of horn of the bloodletting, the prick of the
blood. bloodletting horn, so like a little pinprick, okay? So but a
tiny little pain I had. All right, so that was רבא Rava
*Rava*'s death. Was that, did he have less pain because his brother
רב Rav סאורים *Rav Seorim* spoke to the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves
*Malach HaMavet*? Not exactly clear, but it was minimal pain. Now רבא
*Rava*, presumably an earlier story, רבא הוה יתיב קמיה דרב נחמן *Rava
hava yasiv kamei de-Rav Nachman*, and it's almost an exact parallel story.
רבא *Rava* was sitting in front of רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. חזא
דקא מנמנם *chazai de-kamanamnei*, he saw that רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* was
slipping off. אמר ליה amar lei *Amar lei*, לימא ליה מר Mar,
דלא ליצערן *leimal lei mar de-lo litzara*, so רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*
said to רבא *Rava*, rather, tell him, you know, tell him not
to cause me pain. אמר ליה Amar leih, *Amar lei*, so רבא
*Rava* said back to him, מר לאו אדם חשוב הוא *mar lav
adam chashuv hu*? Aren't you an important person? He'll listen to you,
רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. אמר ליה amar leih, *Amar lei*, so רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* said to him, the one who was dying, מאן
חשיב מאן ספין מאן רקיע *man chashiv, man safin, man rakia*? Who
is, you know, who's important, you know, who has significance, you know,
who has, who has weight? Meaning, the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves *Malach
HaMavet* doesn't pay attention to me, or certainly at the time when
I am dying. But it's a little more poetic response than רבא
*Rava* gave his brother. So what was רקיע *rakia*? Think tells us
to try to figure out the exact etymology, but it basically is
a very poetic way of saying like, you know, nobody's important to
the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves *Malach HaMavet*, or certainly not, nobody, because
then he wouldn't have asked רבא *Rava*, but certainly not when someone
is dying. Okay. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, וחזי לי מר *vichezi lei
mar*.
So then רבא *Rava* said to him, okay, same thing that was
later going to be said back to רבא *Rava*. One wonders why
the order of the stories was reversed. Anyway, he said to רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman*, let the Master appear to me. אתחזי ליה *Itchazi
lei*. So after you die. So רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* appeared to
רבא *Rava*, the disembodied רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. אמר ליה *Amar lei*,
רבא *Rava* said to him, הוה ליה למר צערא *hava lei mar
tzara*? Did you have pain at that time when you died? אמר
ליה *Amar lei*, כמישחל בינתא מחלבא *kinishcha benisa meichalva*, like the drawing
of a hair out of milk. So, which was like much smoother,
so less pain than רבא *Rava* had. Okay. ואמר *Ve-amar*, but even
so, even though it was not painful, it was very, you know,
smooth, the death, אי אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא *i-amar lei Hakadosh
Baruch Hu*, זיל בההוא עלמא כדואית *zil behu alma kade-havayas*, if he
were to tell me to go back to that world, to the,
you know, world of the living, כדואית *kade-havayas*,
like I was, לא בעינא *lo baina*, I don't want to do
that, דנפיש בעיתותיה *denafish bisusei*, I'm too afraid, I would be too
afraid of dying again. Even though my death, right, was not painful,
the, I guess the fear of dying, you know, would be too
great and I'd rather not have to go through that again. Which
is, again, a fascinating insight. רבי אלעזר הוה קאכיל תרומה *Rabbi Elazar
hava ka-achal truma*. Now we're going to get stories about so, so
that was like, you know, it's very well-structured here. First we deal
with the significance of the age of the person dying, the speed
of dying, and then sort of denying the significance of what that,
you know, signifies. Then we get to like the issue about pain
during the time of death and the person sort of losing their,
their status, you know, it's very powerful, like the person, you know,
it's like, like in קהלת *Koheles*, right? You know, you know, king
who's dead, you know, you know, loses all of the, you know,
importance, so the loss of status, you know, the ability to have
an,
to make requests even from the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves *Malach HaMavet*
during that time, but also a discussion there about the, about the,
about the pain or the lack of pain. And now we're going
to turn to negotiating with the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves *Malach HaMavet*.
So let's take a look. So רבי אלעזר הוה קאכיל תרומה *Rabbi
Elazar hava ka-achal truma*. רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* was eating תרומה *truma*.
אתחזי ליה *Itchazi lei*, the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves. *Malach HaMavet* appeared
to him. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, תרומה קאכילנא *truma kachlina*, he says,
don't bother me, I'm eating תרומה *truma*, I'm doing a מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah*, you can't get me now. ולאו קודש איקרי *Velav kodesh ikri*?
It's called something holy, so how can you interfere with this? חבליה
שעתא *Chavlei sha'ata*. So the moment passed. So presumably it means like,
so that's like a really good story, which means like, okay, maybe
he didn't come back till ten years later, as opposed to other
stories where it's just a temporary pushing of the guy, pushing of
the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves *Malach HaMavet* off. Okay. רב ששת אתחזי
ליה בשוקא *Rav Sheshes itchazi lei beshuka*. To רב ששת *Rav Sheshes*
the מלאך המות Malach Hamoves. *Malach HaMavet* appeared in the marketplace, ready
to take, you know, there he was, you know, with the scythe
and the whole thing, ready to slay him down in the marketplace.
So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* said to
him, בשוקא כבהמה *beshuka kebeheima*? So you're going to kill me in
the marketplace like an animal? That's not a place for me to
die. איתא לגבאי ביתא *Isa legabei beisa*. Come to my house, we'll
take care of it there. Okay, and presumably that's what happened. Rav,
what? Wasn't רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* blind? Oh, that's a good point.
And רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* became demented. He's, he's pretty
clear over here.
All right, okay, I haven't been thinking about that, all very good
points, all very good points. At the time when he, you know,
had his faculties. But I don't know if you need natural sight
to see the מלאך המות *Malach HaMavet*. Certainly doesn't, certainly doesn't help
people with good natural sight. What?
You don't see the animal in the שוק *shuk*.
Well, yeah. Okay. רב אשי אתחזי *Rav Ashi itchazi*, well, to, I
mean he means like, it doesn't necessarily mean there were animals around.
Anyway, yeah. Okay. רב אשי אתחזי ליה בשוקא *Rav Ashi itchazi lei
beshuka*. He appeared to רב אשי *Rav Ashi* in the marketplace. אמר
ליה *Amar lei*, אתרח לי תלתין יומין *itrich li tlasin yomi*. Wait,
give me thirty days, ואהדרי לתלמודאי *ve-ahadri tamudai*, so I can חזר
*chazer* all of my learning, I can review all of my learning.
דאמריתו *De-amrisu*, because we say, אשרי מי שבא לכאן ותלמודו בידו *Ashrei
mi sheba lekan
vetalmudo beyado*. Praised is he who comes here to Heaven with all
of his learning in his hand. So give me thirty days, I'll
חזר *chazer* ש"ס *shas* and then I'll be ready to die. Okay.
So ביום תלתין *be-yom tlasin*... So fine he showed up on day
thirty. So אמר ליה מאי כולי האי mai kulei hai what's the
big rush you know so anyway so he says no so the
answer was כדדחקא רגלי דבר נשן kedachaka raglei d'bar nassan you're pushing
the legs of of Bar Nassan meaning that Bar Nassan is going
to now be taking over for you in the academy and you're
the fact that you're still alive is preventing him from taking his
rightful place. דאין מלכות נוגעת בחברתה אפילו כמלא נימא d'ein malchus nogaas
bachaverta afilu k'mlo nima and one kingship cannot touch the other even
like a hairbreadth meaning you know he can't rise to his prominence
as long as you're alive you're not being fair to him. Does
not say what happened after this but presumably he died. רב חסדא
לא הוה יכיל ליה Rav Chisda lo hava yachil lei so the
מלאך המות was not did not have power over
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. דלא הוה שתיק פומיה מגירסא d'lo hava shtik
pumei m'girsa that you know he never stopped learning so the מלאך
המות never had an opening. So one wonders if he ever slept
I don't know. סליק יתיב בארזא דבי רב salik yasiv b'arza d'vei
rav so the מלאך המות went up and he sat in a
cedar tree you know in the house of you know sort of
in the ישיבה. yeshiva. פקע ארזא paka arza the cedar tree burst
I guess on the presence of the מלאך המות ושתיק v'shtik and
for a moment he was silenced ויכיל ליה v'yachil lei and then
the מלאך המות was able to snag him. רבי חייא לא הוה
מצי למיקרב ליה Rabbi Chiya lo hava matzi l'mikrav lei so he
couldn't get close to
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya the מלאך המות. יומא חד אידמי ליה כעניא
yoma chad idmi lei k'anya one day the מלאך המות appeared to
him like a poor person. אתא טרף בבבא ata taraf b'bava he
knocked on the door. אמר ליה אפיקו לי ריפתא amar lei afiku
li rifta so please bring me bread. אפיקו ליה afiku lei he
brought it to him. Now this is not a moment to seize
him either even if he's not learning תורה Torah he's doing a
מצוה. אמר ליה he said to him דלאו קמרחם מר אעניא d'lav
ka merachem mar a'anya so look you have compassion on an עני
ani אההוא גברא מאי לא קמרחם מר a'hahu gavra mai lo ka
merachem mar why don't you have compassion on me I got a
job to do.
So גלי ליה gali lei he revealed himself to him he showed
that he was the מלאך המות. אחוי ליה שוטא דנורא achvei lei
shuta d'nura he showed him a rod of flame. אמצי ליה נפשיה
amtzei lei nafshei so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya had compassion on him
and he made his soul available to him he gave himself over.
All right I'm sure there's a lot to say about those stories
so we're moving on. Okay next משנה mishnah final משנה mishnah here.
All right. נשים nashim all right last משנה mishnah כ"ד עמוד ב'.
kaf daled amud beis.
I am sure.
נשים במועד מענות ולא מטפחות nashim b'moed meanos v'lo metapchos women again
the women who are the professional some of the professional ones who
would do the eulogizing and the wailing and so on so on
חול המועד Chol Hamoed they can do מענות meanos the answering but
they cannot do the slapping we'll see you know with the hand.
רבי ישמעאל אומר הסמוכות למטה מטפחות Rabbi Yishmael omer hasmuchos lamita metapchos
no those that are right near the coffin they can be מטפח
metapeach you know it's not so many of them and that's an
appropriate degree of respect balancing the respect of the dead with the
fact that it's חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. בראשי חדשים בחנוכה ובפורים מענות
ומטפחות b'roshei chodashim b'chanuka u'vpurim meanos u'metapchos but things that are of
lesser weight but still significant days but lesser weight than חול המועד
Chol Hamoed ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh חנוכה Chanuka and פורים Purim they
can both do the מענות meanos which we'll see what that means
in a minute in the גמרא Gemara some type of a responsive
and they can do the
slap. בזה ובזה לא מקוננות b'zeh u'vzeh lo m'konenot but in either
cases neither מועד Moed nor these other days they cannot do קינה
kina we'll see again what all these things are. נקבר המת לא
מענות ולא מטפחות nikbar hames lo meanos v'lo metapchos once the dead
is buried they can't do any of it so it's a degree
what we allow this on חול המועד Chol Hamoed or חנוכה Chanuka
or פורים Purim it's only until the burial.
And now the משנה mishnah explains what are these different things? איזו
היא עינוי eizu hi inuy what is this מענות meanos which we
allow even on חול המועד Chol Hamoed
שכולן עונות כאחת shekulan onot k'achas everybody cries out as one okay
that's a certain degree that's acceptable. מטפחות metapchos which is more problematic
is like the slapping you know on the thigh the slapping with
the hand that makes it obviously much more emphatic much you know
much more public and so on. So what is the קינה kina
that you're not allowed to do on any of these days even
on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh חנוכה Chanuka and פורים? Purim? קינה שאחת
מדברת וכולן עונות אחריה kina she'achas medaberes v'kulan onot achareha one speaks
and then everybody responds back what a type of a responsive recital
which is you know at an experiential level it's more powerful than
everybody saying it
together antiphony is that it? Okay. שנאמר shene'emar as the verse says
ולמדנה בנותיכם נהי ואשה רעותה קינה v'lamdena v'noseichem nehi v'isha re'usa kina
so you'll teach your daughters a moaning and a woman her friend
קינה kina so it's some type of a thing of a responsive
recital. לעתיד לבוא הוא אומר le'asid lavo hu omer but to end
on a positive note in the future it says בלע המות לנצח
ומחה ה' אלהים דמעה מעל כל פנים bila hamaves lanetzach u'macha Hashem
Elokim dima me'al kol panim death should be swallowed up for eternity
and God will wipe tears from all faces something that some people
say at a שבעה shiva house when they're departing also. Interesting I
wanted to point out before we continue that תוספות Tosafos here says
בלע המות לנצח bila hamaves lanetzach look at תוספות Tosafos כדי לסיים
בדבר הטוב k'dei lesayem b'davar hatov now fine you want to end
a מסכת maseches especially one that's been talking about death and morning
with a positive note. But תוספות Tosfot says it's not just the
מסכת Masechet we're ending with a positive note. משום דמועד קטן הוא
סוף סדר מועד. mishum d'Mo'ed Katan hu sof Seder Mo'ed. So he
says this was the last מסכת Masechet on סדר מועד Seder Mo'ed
because often because חגיגה Chagiga and מועד קטן Mo'ed Katan have the
same number of פרקים. perakim. So it's not clear which one is
last, right? And it was so therefore so תוספות Tosfot has has
this as last, and because very often not מסכתות masechtos are always
always end on a good note, sometimes they do, like if you
think about תענית Taanis after the whole thing about תענית Taanis spoke
about לא היו ימים טובים בישראל, lo hayu yamim tovim b'Yisrael, right?
ט"ו באב Tu B'Av and כיום הכיפורים k'Yom Hakippurim and ט"ו באב,
Tu B'Av, you know, כיום הכיפורים וט"ו באב. k'Yom Hakippurim v'Tu B'Av.
So, ט"ו באב וכיום הכיפורים, Tu B'Av v'k'Yom Hakippurim, so that was
also ending a מסכת masechet on a good note. But תוספות Tosfot
wants to see that we're also ending the סדר מועד Seder Mo'ed
on a good note. Okay, but that's an interesting question, which is
the last מסכת masechet of סדר מועד. Seder Mo'ed. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, מאי אמרין? mai amrin? Now back
to, remember before we had הספדים, hespedim, eulogies which were very poetic.
Here we're having the wailing, but also there's a verbal component. It's
not just wailing, there's some type of a responsive, there's things that
are being said. So it's not the same degree of poetry as
the הספד, hesped, but there's still we still want to know, so
what's said, what's said during this מענוות me'anot and this קינה? kina?
So presumably, so what do they say? So אמר רב, amar Rav,
so רב says, וי לאזלא וי לחבילא. vaye l'azla vaye l'chavila. Woe
to the one who is departing, woe to the sort of wounding,
the loss. If you want, you can go see in Soncino also
poetic rendition of all of this. אמר רבא, amar Rava, נשי דשכנציב,
nashei d'Shnitziv, the women of this place, שכנציב, Shnitziv, אמרין, amrin, they
say הכי. hachi. וי לאזלא
וי לחבילא. vaye l'azla vaye l'chavila. Woe to those, to the one
who is going, woe to the wounding. ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, נשי
דשכנציב אמרין, nashei d'Shnitziv amrin, גוד גרמא מככא, gud garma mikacha, remove
the bone from the jaw, or from the pot, ונמטי מיא לאנתיכי,
v'namtei maya l'antichi, and bring the water to the kettle. So, what
that's supposed to mean is
unclear. רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says somehow the bone from the pot
somehow suggests the death, and the water to the kettle is the
soul back to its source. The soul goes back up to heaven.
There are other explanations, like Soncino says something like it means remove
the bone from the pot, not from the jaw, and it means
like we don't have to cook for this guy anymore because he's
dying and the water in the kettle is because we need the
hot water now for like the טהרה taharah process and so on.
So, I don't know. I think actually the רבנו גרשום's Rabbeinu Gershom
explanation is a little nicer, a little more metaphorical. ואמר רבא, v'amar
Rava, and רבא says, נשי דשכנציב אמרין, nashei d'Shnitziv amrin, אטיפי כסות
טורא, atifi kessut tura,
wrap yourself and cover yourself, you mountains, דבר רמי ובר רברבי הוא,
d'bar rami u'bar ravrevi hu, because this person was a was a,
you know, a great person, like the son of heights and of
elevated places. So one of your, you know, one of you of
these high elevated places has died, so cover yourselves in mourning. ואמר
רבא, v'amar Rava, נשי דשכנציב אמרין, nashei d'Shnitziv amrin, שייולי איצטלא דמילתא,
shayulei itztala d'milsa, borrow a cloak of like of linen, לבר חורין
דשלימו זוודיה, l'bar chorin d'shalimu zavdeh, to a free
person because his like his, you know, his sustenance or, you know,
his portion is complete. Which basically means get this person his shrouds,
he's now free from this physical world, right? So his needs of
sustenance, he's been freed from, and now prepare for him the shrouds.
ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, נשי דשכנציב אמרין, nashei d'Shnitziv amrin, רהיט ונפיל
אמעברא, rahit v'nafil a'mabra, run and fall by the by like the
ferry,
וזיפותא יזיף, v'ziphusa yazif, and borrow the money. So to me, I
don't know exactly what this means, like the bridge crossing over into
the other end, it's what's that whole myth about?
The
River Styx, and you have to pay him with a, right, with
the, right, the coin in the eyes. To me, this is what
that evokes, but I don't exactly get, you know, what the I
mean whatever the מפרשים mefarshim try to give some, you know, what
this exactly signifies. ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, נשי דשכנציב אמרין, nashei d'Shnitziv
amrin,
אחנא תגרי, achna tagrei, what? Where's
this? I know, apparently they were the ones that wrote the קינות
kinos for the rest of the world. Okay,
שכנציב, Shnitziv, I have no idea. אחנא תגרי אזבזגי מיבדקו. achna tagrei
azavzegi mivadku. So, ugh, I forget what this means. Can somebody read
me the English they have for this one?
What?
And אחנא תגרי achna tagrei is it?
Right, our brothers' merchants searched at the customs house.
Oh, you'll be searched at the customs house, or maybe you'll be
examined. Oh, right, right, right. Okay. So basically, so presumably, you know,
you're going to be checked about your wares, you know, so you're
coming to the world to come and they're going to do a
whole audit about inventory, exactly. Okay. ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, נשי דשכנציב
אמרין,
nashei d'Shnitziv
amrin, מותא כי מותא ומרעין חבולה. mota ki mota u'marein chavula. Death
like death, meaning the, you know, death will happen and it and
and, you know, and painful is its injury, you know? So, yeah,
you know, people are dying and it's I don't know, there's got
to be a better how do they read it there?
Is it death or that death at the end of the quest
or bruises are the rate of entrance?
Okay, that's making it
poetic.
Right, so death is like death...
One
death is like another and the suffer—what?
Suffering is the interest
payment, oh, from like לא שחבול, lo shachavol, חבול chavol meaning
like collateral. Oh, that's interesting. Okay. So, oh, maybe that's how—did they
translate חבילה chavila that way as also?
This was the one before, where רבה ואיתימא רב פפא זבינא ורהיטי—it's
Rabba ve'isayma Rav Pappa zevina vehiti all like merchants. And he runs
before, he falls across the barrels when you don't have enough money
to, like, you know, pay for his burial shroud. And then they
say the next one
was אבא, Abba, the merchant's nephew, בשמים יפשפשו bashamayim yepashpeshu meaning, you
know, heaven will search to see that you've done good deeds.
Yeah. That was clear. But what do they say for the first
one, which says ווי לאזלא ווי לחבילה? vai la'azla vai lachavila? Do
they read חבילה chavila as wounding, or do they read חבילה chavila
as collateral?
The very first line. 'Woe
for the loss, woe for the security.'
The security. So they read it as security and collateral. Okay, I
was reading it as חבלה, chavala, but here I hear that the
reading is collateral,
like your life is given to you and ultimately you have to
pay it back to God.
Okay, so they say security. Security.
Okay, so I stand corrected then. Okay, so that makes sense here
too, like one death is like another, and you know, and the
suffering is collateral, like this is how we, you know, pay back
the life that we're given to God. תניא, Tanya, היה רבי מאיר
אומר, haya Rabi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir used to say, טוב ללכת
אל בית אבל, tov lalechet el beit avel, okay, so obviously he
didn't say that, Kohelet said that, but he would quote that. Actually,
it's interesting in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, one of the היה אומר
haya omers is just a פסוק. pasuk. But anyway, טוב ללכת אל
בית אבל עד והחי יתן אל לבו. tov lalechet el beit avel
ad vehachai yiten el libo. So now he explicated it the following
way: דברים של מיתה, devarim shel mita, these matters of death you
should put onto your heart if you're the living, consider these matters.
דיספוד יספדוהו, deyasped yispedunei, a person who eulogizes others will be eulogized.
דיקבר יקברונהו, deyekaver yikverunei, if one who buries others, he'll be buried.
דיטען יטענונהו, deyit'an yit'anunei, if somebody carries the burden, presumably like, you
know,
in the burial, like the coffin, you know, he'll be carried, or
they might
read—yeah. דידל ידלונהו, deyadal yedalunei, the person who lifts up his voice
in the funeral, people will lift up their voices when he dies.
ואיכא דאמרי, ve'ika d'amri, others say, דלא ידל ידלונהו, delo yadal yedalunei,
if one doesn't lift up, meaning doesn't lift himself up, does not
act in a haughty manner, then he will be lifted up, you
know, when he dies. דכתיב כי טוב אמר לך עלה הנה, dichtiv
ki tov amar lecha aleh heina, because they say to you, 'Come
up here.' Anyway, the whole פסוק pasuk talks about that, about, you
know, people raising someone up who, and you'll be raised to heights
if you kept yourself humble in your life. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
כשמתו בניו של רבי ישמעאל, keshemetu banav shel Rabi Yishmael, נכנסו ארבעה
זקנים לנחמו. nichnesu arba'a zekeinim lenachamo. Now we get to a discussion
of ניחום אבלים. nichum aveilim. Okay, because we're, you know, talked about
all this more performative wailing, and we also talked about poetic הספדים.
hespedim. Now we're going to see that ניחום אבלים, nichum aveilim, at
least amongst the rabbis, took a very literary type of an approach.
Okay, so when the children—notice again the plural, we have had this
before, that multiple children die at one time—the children of Rabbi Yishmael
died, four elders came to
consult him: Rabbi Tarfon, Rabbi Yose HaGelili, Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah, and
Rabbi Akiva. אמר להם רבי טרפון, amar lahem Rabi Tarfon, so Rabbi
Tarfon said to them as they were about to go in, דעו
שחכם גדול הוא ובקי באגדות. de'u shechacham gadol hu uvaki be'agadot. You
should know that Rabban Gamliel is a very wise—Rabbi Yishmael, excuse me,
and very knowledgeable in אגדות. agadot. אל יכנס אחד מכם לתוך דברי
חבירו. al yikanes echad mikem letoch divrei chaveiro. Do not interrupt one
another. Not exactly clear to me how those two points are connected,
but anyway, give each one of you an opportunity
to say their תורה. Torah. אמר רבי עקיבא ואני אחרון. amar Rabi
Akiva va'ani acharon. I get to go last. פתח רבי ישמעאל ואמר.
patach Rabi Yishmael ve'amar.
So when they came in, Rabbi Yishmael started the conversation, the mourner,
and he said, רבו עונותיו תכפו אבליו. rabu avonotav tachfu aveilav. Great
are his, meaning his own, great are his sins,
the mournings have piled up one on the other. הטריח רבותיו, hetriach
rabotav, and now he made his
rabbis—he put them out that they had had to come and pay
a שבעה shiva call. פעם ראשונה ושנייה, pa'am rishona ushniya, once and
even a second time, because for two children. נענה רבי טרפון ואמר,
ne'ena Rabi Tarfon ve'amar, Rabbi Tarfon responded and said, ואחיכם כל בית
ישראל יבכו את השרפה. ve'achichem kol beit Yisrael yivku et hasreifa. Right,
this is by Nadav and Avihu. והלא דברים קל וחומר, vehala devarim
kal vachomer, ומה נדב ואביהו שלא עשו אלא מצוה אחת, uma Nadav
ve'Avihu shelo asu ela mitzvah achat, they did just one mitzvah, דכתיב,
dichtiv, that we know of, ויקריבו בני אהרן את הדם אליו, vayikrivu
benei Aharon et hadam eilav, and nevertheless the whole people mourned for
their death. כך בניו של רבי ישמעאל על אחת כמה וכמה, kach
banav shel Rabi Yishmael al achat kama vechama, how much more so
your children and considering all the מצוות mitzvot that they did, how
much more so all of us will mourn for their death.
נענה רבי יוסי הגלילי ואמר, ne'ena Rabi Yose HaGelili ve'amar, וספדו לו
כל ישראל וקברו אותו. vesafdu lo kol Yisrael vekaveru oto. So all
of Israel eulogized and buried him. This is the father of Aviya
the son of
Jeroboam. והלא דברים קל וחומר, vehala devarim kal vachomer, מה אביה בן
ירבעם שלא עשה אלא דבר אחד טוב, ma Aviya ben Yerovam shelo
asa ela davar echad tov, he did—here he really only did one
good thing in his life, דכתיב, dichtiv, as it says, יען נמצא
בו דבר טוב. ya'an nimtza bo davar tov. because a good matter
has been found has found has been found in him, so כך,
kach, so nevertheless there was a whole of Israel mourned for his
death,
בנו של רבי ישמעאל קל וחומר. Bno shel Rabbi Yishmael kal vachomer.
How much more so for the children of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
So מאי דבר טוב, mai davar tov, now we're a little bit
digressing, what was that good thing that he did? וזה רבי חנינא
בר פפא. ve'ze Rabbi Chanina bar Papa. חד אמר שביטל משמרתו ועלה
לרגל. chad amar she'bitel mishmarto ve'ala laregel. He was on duty to
watch and to prevent people from being עולה לרגל ole laregel because
that's the whole thing ירבעם בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat did is
he split up the people and perceived that they shouldn't go to
the רגל, regel, and you know, he erected the עגלים. agalim.
So presumably we're having that his son here, אביה, Aviyah, before he
was king, you know, was there to to be he prevented people
from, he was on guard duty, and he decided, "I'm leaving the
guard duty," and he himself was עולה לרגל. ole laregel. וחד אמר,
vechad amar, the other says שביטל פרדסאות שהושיב ירבעם אביו על הדרכים.
she'bitel pardesaot she'hoshib Yerovam aviv al hadrachim. He even did a more
important thing. He actually caused he made the guards the watchmen stop,
he annulled that, not just his own duty, he annulled the whole
institution of putting of having them there on the ways to stop
people from being עולה לרגל, ole laregel, שלא יעלו ישראל לרגל. she'lo
ya'alu Yisrael laregel. Okay, back to our point. תניא רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה אומר, tanya Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya now says, בשלום תמות ובמשרפות אבותיך המלכים הראשונים
אשר היו לפניך כן ישרפו לך, beshalom tamut ubemisfrot avotecha hamelachim harishonim
asher hayu lefanecha ken yisrefu lach, I think, anyway. So anyway, in
the so this is talking about צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, you will die in
peace and you will be burnt on the like the pyres that
your that you know the earlier kings were burnt. והלא דברים קל
וחומר. vehalo devarim kal vachomer. We're not dealing with the problem about
burning about burning a body. והלא דברים קל וחומר ומה צדקיה מלך
יהודה שלא עשה אלא מצוה אחת, vehalo devarim kal vachomer uma Tzidkiya
melech Yehuda she'lo asa ela mitzvah achat, and צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu only did
one good thing, says, well, presumably he did more but we only
the Torah only records one, because שהעלה ירמיהו מן הטיט, she'he'ela Yirmeyahu
min hatit, he raised ירמיהו Yirmeyahu from the from the mud,
כך, kach, and nevertheless he had this honor in his death and
everybody mourned for him, בנו של רבי ישמעאל אחת כמה וכמה. Bno
shel Rabbi Yishmael achat kama vechama. How much more so the sons
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. You're getting a you're you're noting a
theme here. תניא רבי עקיבא אומר, tanya Rabbi Akiva omer, now רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, now of course רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, "I
want to go last," so we're expecting something of significant difference, or
you know, let's take a look at what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says. ביום ההוא יגדל המספד בירושלים כמספד הדדרימון בבקעת מגידו. bayom hahu
yigdal hamisped b'Yerushalayim kemisped Hadadrimon bevik'at Megido. On that day the, you
know, and this is sort of like a a, you know, a
vision of אחרית הימים, acharit hayamim, you know, the wailing in ירושלים
Yerushalayim will be as great as the wailing of הדדרימון Hadadrimon in
the valley of מגידו. Megido. Now, we know this הדדרימון, Hadadrimon, but
he had nothing to do with the valley of מגידו. Megido. ואמר
רב יוסף, ve'amar Rav Yosef, and רב יוסף says, as obviously the
גמרא Gemara insert in because it's a little later than רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, אלמלא תרגומא דהאי קרא לא הוה ידענא מאי קאמר, ilmale
targuma dehai kra lo havah yadana mai ka'amar, were it not for
the Aramaic translation of this verse,
I wouldn't understand what's הדדרימון Hadadrimon doing in בבקעת מגידו. bevik'at Megido.
So, but here's the Aramaic translation: בעידנא ההיא יסגי מספדא בירושלים כמספדא
דאחאב בר עמרי דקטל יתיה הדדרימון בר טברימון וכמספדא דיאשיהו בר אמון
דקטל יתיה פרעה חגירא בבקעת מגידו. be'idna hahi yisgei mispeda bi'Yerushalayim kemispeda
de'Achav bar Omri de'katal yetei Hadadrimon bar Tabrimon veche'mispeda de'Yoshiyahu bar Amon
de'katal yetei Paroh Chagira be'vik'at Megido. In that day the wailing, you
know, the eulogizing in ירושלים Yerushalayim will go so great,
like
the wailing of
אחאב בר עמרי Achav bar Omri that was slaughtered by הדדרימון, Hadadrimon,
so the מספד misped of הדדרימון Hadadrimon is the victim of הדדרימון,
Hadadrimon, אחאב, Achav, וכמספד veche'misped and בבקעת מגידו bevik'at Megido is a
second thing, וכמספד דיאשיהו בר אמון דקטל יתיה פרעה חגירא בבקעת מגידו,
veche'mispeda de'Yoshiyahu bar Amon de'katal yetei Paroh Chagira be'vik'at Megido, and the
and the wailing and the mourning of יאשיהו Yoshiyahu who was slain
in בבקעת מגידו bevik'at Megido by פרעה חגירא. Paroh Chagira. Two different
things. So that's how we resolve that that problem. Okay, back to
the back to the ברייתא braita here. והלא דברים קל וחומר, vehalo
devarim kal vachomer, but now we've established that it's referring to אחאב.
Achav. ומה אחאב מלך ישראל שלא עשה אלא דבר אחד טוב, uma
Achav melech Yisrael she'lo asa ela davar echad tov, אחאב Achav only
did one good thing, דכתיב והמלך היה
מעמד במרכבה נוכח ארם. de'chtiv ve'hamelech hayah ma'amad bamerkava nochach Aram. The
king was standing in the chariot opposite ארם, Aram, so and that
he was presumably, you know, leading the people, and
and or his רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, making sure that they
would not sort of stumble somehow, anyway he was taking a leadership
role in that moment. So כך, kach, and nevertheless all of the
people, like, it was a wailed and mourned his death, בנו של
רבי ישמעאל אחת כמה וכמה. Bno shel Rabbi Yishmael achat kama vechama.
How much more so the children of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. You're
getting a you're you're noting a theme here. Anyway, it does not
seem like anything significantly different than what anybody else said. Don't exactly
understand why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva insisted on going last, or even
if he didn't just why that was recorded in the story. Like,
you're expecting for something radically different at the end.
Anyway,
I don't get it. All right, anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, אמר רבא לרבה בר מרי, Amar Rava leRabba
bar Mari, Rava said to Rabba bar Mari. חזי בי צדקיהו, Chazi
bei Tzidkiyahu, it says by Tzidkiyahu, בשלום תמות, B'shalom tamut, you will
die in peace, וכתיב, Uchtiv, but then it says דסמיוהו לצדקיהו עיניה,
desamyuhu leTzidkiyahu eineih, that Tzidkiyahu's eyes were, you
know, blinded, you know, by מלך בבל? Melech Bavel? So אמר ליה,
הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, Hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, this is
what
Rabbi Yochanan says: no, שמת נבוכדנצר בימיו, shemet Nevuchadnezzar beyamav, even though
he was blinded, there was a sense of dying in peace because
he outlived Nebuchadnezzar.
Okay, ואמר רבא לרבה בר מרי, Ve’amar Rava leRabba bar Mari, כתיב
ביה ביאשיהו, ketiv bei beYoshiyahu, it says
by Yoshiyahu, לכן הנני אוספך על אבותיך ונאספת אל קברותיך בשלום, lachen
hineni osefcha al avotecha vene’asafta el kivrotecha beshalom, you’ll be gathered into
your grave in peace,
וכתיב, uchtiv, ויורו המורים
למלך יאשיהו, vayoru hamorim lamelech Yoshiyahu, the archers shot through King Yoshiyahu,
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, ve’amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, שעשאוהו ככברה,
she’asu’hu kichvara,
that they basically shot him so much they made him like a
sieve. That’s going and dying in peace? And so אמר ליה, הכי
אמר רבי יוחנן, hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, שלא חרב בית המקדש בימיו.
shelo charav Beit HaMikdash beyamav. No, what it means to die in
peace is at least the temple wasn’t destroyed in his days. Now,
by the way, I think in addition to just dealing with problematic
פסוקים, Pesukim, what this is doing is also an answer to what
we had on the עמוד א', Amud Alef, you know, looking for
various סימנים Simanim of what does it mean that somebody died this
way. Somebody died and had their eyes poked out or somebody died
and they were shot through, you know, with arrows, presumably you would
interpret that as a bad סימן, Siman, I would imagine. But here
it's saying you can have those things happen and still say he
died in peace, you know, he, you know, he, you know, and
he went to his fathers in peace, you know, it's all question
of some perspective. Okay, so he outlived Nebuchadnezzar, okay, the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash wasn’t destroyed, so you know, it's quite I think this
is a very strong response to what happened before, to the discussion
before. Okay, ואמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Ve’amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, שעשאוהו... she’asu’hu... Oh, I
just did that. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, אין מנחמין משום
לומר דבר עד שיפתח אבל. ein menachamin mishum lomar davar ad sheyiphtach
avel. This is a real הלכה, Halacha, the consolers should not say
anything until until the אבל Avel starts. You wait, you know, well
we'll take a look.
שנאמר, She’ne’emar, because you know for obvious reasons, A you want to
know maybe he’s not ready to hear people, maybe you know, again
it’s the real issue of putting oneself in the other person’s place,
you don’t know what sort of how to start the conversation meaning
not that you might think you know how to start the conversation
but it might not be where the אבל Avel wants to start
the conversation. So anyway you have to wait for him to begin.
שנאמר אחרי כן פתח איוב את פיהו, She’ne’emar acharei ken patach Iyov
et pihu,
so after all the tragedy finally איוב Iyov began to speak, והדר,
vahadar, ויען אליפז התימני, vayaan Eliphaz HaTeimani, and then it was Eliphaz's
response. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, מניין לאבל שמיסב בראש? minayin
le’avel shemeisev berosh?
How do you know that when you sit at the table the
אבל Avel sits at the head, you know, presumably in the שבעה
Shiva house, but that's maybe a surprise, maybe you would assume that
because of his state of אבילות Avelut he should not be at
the head? שנאמר, She’ne’emar, אבחר דרכם ואשב ראש ואשכון כמלך בגדוד, evchar
darkam ve’eshev rosh ve’eshkon kemelech begdud,
I will choose the place and I will sit at the head
and I will dwell like a king amongst the troop, כאשר אבלים
ינחם, ka’asher avelim yenachem,
like mourners will, now the literal meaning is, will console, not will
be consoled. So the same way as ינחם, yenachem, אחריני משמע, achrini
mashma, it means console others. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, ינוחמו כתיב. Yenu’chamu ketiv. Okay, you can read it
will be consoled even though that's not how it's normally read. Anyway
but it speaks about sitting at the head and comparing it to
mourners, so from there we learn this idea. מר זוטא אמר מהכא,
Mar Zutra amar me’hacha, וסר מרזח סרוחים. vesar marze’ach seruchim. מרזח נעשה
שר לסרוחים. Marze’ach na’aseh sar leseruchim.
So and we’ll turn away, oh, what's the translation they give for
this? Somebody have the translation there?
For what? וסר מרזח סרוחים? vesar marze’ach seruchim?
Pass away...
excess of mourning will approach... Okay.
Huh?
Will be removed...
excess of mourning will approach... will approach... וסר Vesar means יסור, yasur,
סרוחים... seruchim... yeah, and then מרזח נעשה שר וסרוחים, marze’ach na’aseh sar
veseruchim, it will become prince
of the exiled.
מרזח Marze’ach they're reading as the mourner? Okay. All right, okay, מר,
okay, okay, so somehow anyway מרזח Marze’ach is read as the mourner
and the שר לסרוחים sar leseruchim is the prince among them, so
he has the chief place. Again it's a little ironic, right? Okay,
yeah, he's the sort of, you know, he's the center of attention
but to give him this sense of like being the head is
a little bit ironic which is why they're looking for these verses.
Steinsaltz says it's unclear. Thank you.
Oh, okay, I go with Steinsaltz. אמר רב חמא בר חנינא, Amar
Rav Chama bar Chanina, מניין לחתן שמיסב בראש? minayin lechatan shemeisev berosh?
Now this of course makes a lot more sense, okay, and it
is fascinating and maybe it's worth pointing out that there's partly maybe
what's going on, the comparisons between אבילות Avelut and marriage, right? You
have the idea of the seven days, you have, you know,
and you even have a sense of the שלושים, Shloshim, שבעה ושלושים
Shiva ve’Shloshim and י"ב חודש Yud-Beit Chodesh as far as הלכות Halachos
in marriage as well when you say certain ברכות Brachos and the
you know sort of שהשמחה במעונו shehasimcha bim’ono and similar types of
things. So there are all of these sort of parallels and comparisons
and here we’re sort of saying, and then there’s the whole question
about, you know, for ברכת אבלים Birchat Avelim you need ten, does
the mourner count as one of the ten? For ברכת חתנים Birchat
Chatanim you need ten, does the חתן Chatan count for one of
the ten? There are these sort of parallel discussions. So here the
idea that a חתן chatan is יושב בראש yoshev berosh makes sense.
Again I don't exactly know what to do with this whole idea
of the אבל יושב בראש. avel yoshev berosh. So let's take a
look. מניין לחתן שמיסב בראש? Minayin lechatan shemeisev berosh? שנאמר כחתן יכהן
פאר, She’ne’emar kechatan yichahen pe’er, like a bridegroom he will like, you
know... decked himself with glory but with particular focus on the word
כהן kohein here: מה כהן בראש אף חתן בראש. ma kohein b'rosh
af choson b'rosh. וכהן גופיה מנלן? vekohein gufeih minalan? Where do we
know a כהן kohein is sort of given the head
place? דתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל: detanya devei rabbi Yishmael: וקדשתו לכל דבר
שבקדושה. vekidashto lechol davar shebikdusha. You shall sanctify him, all matters of
sanctity. לפתוח ראשון, liftoach rishon, he gets to open first; ולברך ראשון,
ulvareich rishon, bless first; וליטול מנה יפה בראשון, velitol mana yafa berishon,
to take the first portion. So a חתן choson is given the
same idea. So the חתן choson is the sort of the, you
know, the guest of honor, and he sits at the head. And
ironically, the אבל avel is the guest of honor in his שבעה
shiva house, and he sits at the head. Again, I don't exactly
know what to do with this. Okay. אמר רבי חנינא: amar Rabbi
Chanina: קשה יציאת נשמה מן הגוף. kasha yetziat neshama min haguf. We
were talking about easy deaths; now we're going to talk about the
difficulty. The difficulty of the soul leaving the body
כציפורי בפי ושט, ketzipori befi veshet, like sort of the, the rope
that's in the, that's in the, what's it called, the thing of
the of the mast, the rig of the mast. So like trying
to like, you know, the friction in trying to pull that out,
so that's how difficult it is. רבי יוחנן אמר: Rabbi Yochanan amar:
כפיטורי בפי ושט, kifituri befi veshet, like I think it means the
sail that's in, that's attached to the mast. So they're using the
same type of imagery. ואמר רבי לוי בר חיתא: ve'amar Rabbi Levi
bar Chita: הנפטר מן המת, haniftar min hamet, if somebody takes his
leave from a person who is has died, לא יאמר לו לך
לשלום, lo yomar lo leich l'shalom, like you say at a funeral,
you should not say go to peace, אלא לך בשלום, ela leich
b'shalom, go in peace, because the person's already in a state of
שלום. shalom. הנפטר מן החי, haniftar min hachai, and when one leaves
from of the living, לא יאמר לו לך בשלום, lo yomar lo
leich b'shalom, don't go in peace, which is now we understand something
one says to the to the dead, אלא לך לשלום, ela leich
l'shalom, go towards peace. So I guess we're always seeking, you know,
as long as we're alive, we're always striving, we're always seeking, we're
never in a static state. הנפטר מן המת לא יאמר לו לך
לשלום אלא לך בשלום שנאמר ואתה תבוא אל אבותיך בשלום. haniftar min
hamet lo yomar lo leich l'shalom ela leich b'shalom shene'emar v'ata tavo
el avotecha b'shalom. Right, so that's said when Abraham dies, you'll come
with peace. הנפטר מן החי, haniftar min hachai, but it's talking about
what that status will be, לא יאמר לו לך בשלום אלא לך
לשלום שהרי דוד אמר לאבשלום לך בשלום והלך ונתלה. lo yomar lo
leich b'shalom ela leich l'shalom sheharei David amar l'Avshalom leich b'shalom vehalach
venitla. So he was the death of Absalom and Absalom died. יתרו
שנאמר למשה
לך לשלום הלך והצליח. Yitro shene'emar l'Moshe leich l'shalom halach vehitzliach. Moshe
was successful. ואמר רבי לוי: ve'amar Rabbi Levi: כל היוצא מבית הכנסת
לבית המדרש, kol hayotzei mibeit haknesset l'beit hamidrash, so now to end
in a positive note, anybody goes from synagogue to a study hall,
ומבית המדרש לבית הכנסת, umibeit hamidrash l'beit haknesset, from a study hall
to the synagogue, זוכה ומקבל פני שכינה, zoche umekabel pnei shechina, will
receive the presence of the Shechina, presumably meaning when they die, or
maybe it means in the בית כנסת beit knesset and בית מדרש,
beit midrash, and it's an interesting question, right? You were talking about
all this things about death and the soul going back to God.
Where do you experience פני שכינה? pnei shechina? So maybe you're experiencing
פני שכינה pnei shechina in the בית המדרש beit hamidrash and the
בית הכנסת. beit haknesset. Not exactly what זוכה ומקבל zoche umekabel though
might mean in the future, so there's a certain ambiguity there. Often
זוכה ומקבל zoche umekabel means after you die you will get this
reward. שנאמר ילכו מחיל אל חיל יראה אל אלהים בציון. shene'emar yelchu
mechayil el chayil yeira'eh el elohim beTzion. Go from strength to strength,
will see God in Zion, and again this is sort of the
לך לשלום. leich l'shalom. As long as a person is living, they
can always be going from strength to strength. The sort of being
static is after one dies. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב:
amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav: תלמידי חכמים אין להם מנוחה.
talmidei chachamim ein lahem menucha. So now, now we say that idea
of always striving and going to a higher level, for תלמידי חכמים,
talmidei chachamim, it doesn't even even in their death that continues, that
they're always going higher and higher. They don't have peace אפילו עולם
הבא, afilu olam haba, שנאמר ילכו מחיל אל חיל יראה אל אלהים
בציון, shene'emar yelchu mechayil el chayil yeira'eh el elohim beTzion, even when
they see God in the future, although עולם הבא olam haba might
not mean death, it might be the world to come after משיח,
Moshiach, but they will continue to continue to grow and to strive.
הדרן עלך אלו מגלחין וסליקא לה מסכת מועד קטן. hadran alach eilu
megalchin uslika la masechet moed katan. What we're going to do the
הדרן עלך hadran alach now? Is there a קדיש? kaddish? Okay.